A Guide to the Virginia Dental Association records, 1870-1985
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
- Annual Meetings, 1924-1980 (Box 21-24)
  - Local Arrangements and Program Committee Records 1929-1939, 1954-1956, 1965 (Box 23-24)
    - 1932 Program Committee, 1932 (Box-folder 24:1)
    - 1934 Program Committee, 1934 (Box-folder 24:2)
    - 1935 Program Committee, 1935 (Box-folder 24:3)
    - 1936 Program Committee, 1936 (Box-folder 24:4)
    - 1937 Program Committee, 1937 (Box-folder 24:5)
    - 1939 Program Committee, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 24:6)
    - 1954 Program Committee, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 24:7)
    - 1955 Program Committee, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 24:8)
    - 1956 Program Committee, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 24:9)
    - 1965 Program Committee, 1965 (Box-folder 24:10)
  - Programs, 1924-1979 (Box 24)
    - Programs, 1920s (Box-folder 24:11)
    - Programs, 1930s (Box-folder 24:12)
    - Programs, 1940s (Box-folder 24:13-14)
    - Programs, 1950s (Box-folder 24:15-16)
    - Programs, 1960s (Box-folder 24:17-19)
    - Programs, 1970s (Box-folder 24:20)
    - Programs, 1908-1912 and 1950-1964, Two bound volumes. (Not boxed, on shelf.)
  - Meeting Exhibitors, 1927-1980 (Box 25)
    - 1927 Meeting Exhibitors, 1927 (Box-folder 25:1)
    - 1928 Meeting Exhibitors, 1928 (Box-folder 25:2)
    - 1929 Meeting Exhibitors, 1929 (Box-folder 25:3)
    - 1930 Meeting Exhibitors, 1929-1930 (Box-folder 25:4)
    - 1931 Meeting Exhibitors, 1930-1932 (Box-folder 25:5)
    - 1932 Meeting Exhibitors, 1932 (Box-folder 25:6)
    - 1933 Meeting Exhibitors, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 25:7)
    - 1934 Meeting Exhibitors, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 25:8)
    - 1939 Meeting Exhibitors, 1939 (Box-folder 25:9)
    - 1955 Meeting Exhibitors, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 25:10)
    - 1956 Meeting Exhibitors, 1955-1956 (Box-folder 25:11)
    - 1966 Meeting Exhibitors, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 25:12)
    - 1972 Meeting Exhibitors, 1972 (Box-folder 25:13)
    - 1974 Meeting Exhibitors, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 25:14)
    - 1977 Meeting Exhibitors, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 25:15)
    - 1978 Meeting Exhibitors, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 25:16)
    - 1979 Meeting Exhibitors, 1979 (Box-folder 25:17)
    - 1980 Meeting Exhibitors, 1980 (Box-folder 25:18)
- Correspondence, 1917-1985 (Box 25-28)
  - General VDA Correspondence 1917-1975 (Box 25-27)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box-folder 25:19)
    - Correspondence, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 25:20)
    - Correspondence, 1920 (Box-folder 25:21-22)
      Several letters (June 16 and 19, December 2 and 13) between the VDA and the Old Dominion Dental Society discuss allowing blacks membership in the VDA.
    - Correspondence, 1921 (Box-folder 25:23-24)
    - Correspondence, 1923 (Box-folder 25:25)
    - Correspondence, 1924 (Box-folder 26:1-3)
    - Correspondence, 1925 (Box-folder 26:4-5)
    - Correspondence, 1926 (Box-folder 26:6)
    - Correspondence, 1927 (Box-folder 26:7-8)
      A letter dated April 11 states that the VDA has three female members.
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box-folder 26:9)
    - Correspondence, 1929 (Box-folder 26:10)
    - Correspondence, 1930 (Box-folder 26:11)
      Several letters concerning a bill that would more fully define the practice of dentistry and make it illegal for a person to conduct a dental practice under a trade name or corporation and a letter (December 29) from the ADA discussing the difficulties dentists encounter using alcohol in their practices due to Prohibition laws.
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box-folder 26:12)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box-folder 26:13)
      Several letters discussing dental care for school children in the Roanoke area and concerns about advertising dentists.
    - Correspondence, 1933 (Box-folder 26:14)
    - Correspondence, 1934 (Box-folder 26:15)
      Correspondence about lifting the licensing tax on dentists.
    - Correspondence, 1935 (Box-folder 27:1)
    - Correspondence, 1936 (Box-folder 27:2-3)
      A letter (April 17) from J.E. John of the VDA to C.J. Caraballo of Florida asking for guidance in accepting blacks into the state dental society. Caraballos' response (April 23) stated that both Florida and Alabama allowed blacks to attend state meetings as guests and to pay a fee into the treasury to obtain a membership card which entitled them to membership in the ADA as well.
    - Correspondence, 1937 (Box-folder 27:4-6)
      Correspondence includes a letter (April 29) from the Southern California State Dental Association regarding the formation of a National Woman's Auxiliary Board and another letter (November 10) from the ADA regarding the Army Dental Corps bill to increase the number of dentists to improve the level of care and service for military personnel.
    - Correspondence, 1938 (Box-folder 27:7-8)
      Correspondence includes letters regarding the possible formation of a Southern Dental Association, a letter from the American Dental Hygienists' Association asking for names of licensed hygienists (licenses not required in Virginia at that time), and Stephen J. Lewis of the Old Dominion Dental Society asking for a copy of the VDA constitution and the bylaws to use as a guide for reorganizing their group.
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Box-folder 27:9)
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box-folder 27:10)
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box-folder 27:11)
      Includes a letter (May 23) from F. L. Adams of Florida regarding membership of black dentists in the Virginia Association. The letter mentions a proposal to the ADA to provide black dentists with the opportunity to join the ADA via their membership in the National Dental Association.
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box-folder 27:12)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box-folder 27:13)
      Correspondence includes a letter (May 18) from the VDA to Congressman Richard A. Poff expressing their hope that he will vote against the Anti-Fluoridation Bill.
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box-folder 27:14)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box-folder 27:15)
      Includes letters discussing the portion of the VDA bylaws which stated the Executive Council must approve members elected by the component societies. This was in conflict with the ADA bylaws, so an amendment was made stating that the component societies had the final say on members.
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box-folder 27:16)
      Correspondence includes an invitation from the ADA for a US Army sponsored program on nuclear disaster preparedness and the potential of using dentists in a para-medical capacity during an emergency.
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box-folder 27:17)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1961, 1963 (Box-folder 27:18)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1973, 1975 (Box-folder 27:19)
  - Officers' Correspondence and related materials, 1924-1985 (Box 27-28)
    - Clark, Lonnie O. Jr., 1980-1981 (Box-folder 27:19)
      President, 1980; also includes a copy of his President's Address.
    - Delp, W. C., 1927-1928 (Box-folder 27:20)
      President, 1928.
    - Fisher, Elmer O., Jr. 1976-1977 (Box-folder 27:21)
      President, 1977.
    - Fitzhugh, William B. 1977-1979 (Box-folder 28:1-3)
      President, 1978; also includes a copy of his President's Address as well as a few other speeches and clippings.
    - Fletcher, Charles F., 1977-1979 (Box-folder 28:4)
      President, 1979; also includes a photograph, a copy of his President's Address, and clippings.
    - Gregory, Carlton E., 1970-1971 (Box-folder 28:5)
      President, 1971; also includes a copy of his President's Address.
    - Harloe, C. Bruce, 1925, 1933-1934 (Box-folder 28:6)
      Executive Council, 1934; his correspondence mostly pertains to his work to abolish the state dental license tax.
    - Henderson, Myron E., 1970 (Box-folder 28:7)
      President, 1970.
    - Hodges, Harry L., 1983-1985 (Box-folder 28:8)
      President, 1985, also includes a copy of his President's Address and a photograph.
    - Irby, John P., 1939-1940 (Box-folder 28:9)
      President, 1940.
    - John, James E., 1924-1940 (Box-folder 28:10-11)
      President, 1930; Secretary-Treasurer, 1935-1939.
    - Lewis, Jason R., 1972-1974 (Box-folder 28:12)
      President, 1974; also includes a copy of his President's Address and several other speeches.
    - Martone, Alexander L., 1967-1969, 1975 (Box-folder 28:13)
      President, 1969; also includes campaign materials for his 1975 bid for president of the ADA.
    - Michaels, Emanuel W., 1982-1984 (Box-folder 28:14)
      President, 1984; also includes a photograph and a 1984 speech to the MCV dental graduates.
    - Muir, Norbone F., 1934-1936 (Box-folder 28:15)
      President, 1936.
    - Powell, Hume Scott, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 28:16)
      President, 1968.
    - Strickland, Earle W., 1981-1983 (Box-folder 28:17)
      President, 1983; also includes a copy of his President's Address.
    - Traynham, William H., Jr. 1971-1972 (Box-folder 28:18)
      President, 1972; also includes a photograph.
    - Tyree, John C. 1956-1958 (Box-folder 28:19)
      President, 1958.
    - Wash, Atwood Melville, 1928-1935 (Box-folder 28:20)
      Secretary-Treasurer, 1929-1935.
    - Woodford, Curtis R., 1979-1980 (Box-folder 28:21)
    - Upshur, Thomas T., 1971-1973 (Box-folder 28:22)
      President, 1973; also includes a photograph.
- Component Societies, 1931-1978 (Box 29)
  - Component Officers Handbook, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 29:1)
  - Component Societies, Organization 1931-1932 (Box-folder 29:2)
    Correspondence regarding the organization of local dental groups into component societies of the VDA and membership lists.
  - Component Society 1, Virginia Tidewater Dental Association, 1932-1959 (Box-folder 29:3-4)
  - Component Society 2, Peninsula Dental Society, 1932-1959, 1970, and 1977 (Box-folder 29:5)
  - Component Society 3, Southside Virginia Dental Society, 1932-1959, 1973, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 29:6)
  - Component Society 4, Richmond Dental Society, 1933-1959, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 29:7)
  - Component Society 5, Piedmont Dental Society, 1932-1959 (Box-folder 29:8)
  - Component Society 6, Southwest Virginia Dental Society, 1933-1959, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 29:9)
  - Component Society 7, Shenandoah Valley Dental Association, 1931-1959 (Box-folder 29:10)
  - Component Society 8, Northern Virginia Dental Association, 1933-1959, 1969-1978 (Box-folder 29:11-14)
    Materials for component society 8 include correspondence, annual reports, a history of the group, and programs from component meetings.
- Administrative Files, 1919-1984 (Box 29-31, 35-36)
  - Subject Files, 1919-1984 (Box 29-30, 35-36)
    - Bulletin, 1923-1934 (Box-folder 29:15)
    - Clinics, 1930-1939 (Box-folder 29:16)
    - Code of Fair Competition for the Dental Laboratory Industry, National Recovery Administration, 1934 (Box-folder 29:17)
    - Constitution and Bylaws, 1931 (Box-folder 29:18)
    - Conference on Dental Health Education, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 29:19)
      Contains correspondence, meeting minutes, and programs for the planning of the 1952 conference.
    - Court Case: Golec v. Northern Virginia Dental Society, et al., 1976 (Box-folder 29:20)
      This lawsuit was filed in reaction to the charges by the NVDS that Golec had violated the ethics code of the Society by sending announcement cards to area dentist announcing service and staff additions at his practice. The suit was settled, the actions against Golec were expunged from his record, and the appropriate portion of the NVDS Code of Ethics was changed.
    - Deceased Member Records, 1927-1984 (Box 35-36)
      These records contain index cards listing member information including name, address, birth date, college attended, specialty, military service, details of participation in the VDA, and death date. Some records have obituaries attached. To view an Excel spreadsheet of all the dentists listed along with their college, date of graduation, city of practice, date of initial VDA membership, and death date please click here.
    - Dental Hygienists (Box-folder 29:21)
    - Dental Laws of Virginia, 1930, 1950, and 1968 (Box-folder 29:22)
    - Dental Visual Education, 1937 (Box-folder 29:23)
    - Dependents Medical Care Act Public Law 569, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 29:24)
      Correspondence regarding this act and the designation of certain military bases as "rural areas" so that dependents on base could receive treatment from a military dentist.
    - Five Point Program, 1928 (Box-folder 29:25)
      A dental care program for school aged children
    - Healthguard Program, U.S. Junior Chamber of Commerce, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 30:1)
    - Insurance Plans, 1926-1930, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 30:2-4)
    - Invitations, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 30:5)
    - Jamestown Festival, 350th Anniversary Contributions, 1937 (Box-folder 30:6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 30:7)
    - National Health Conference, 1938 (Box-folder 30:8)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 30:9)
    - Obituaries and Resolutions on Death, 1927-1931 (Box-folder 30:10)
    - Officer Lists, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 30:11)
    - Photographs (Box-folder 30:12)
    - Program, International Dental Congress, Vienna, 1936 (Box-folder 30:13)
    - Reprints (Box-folder 30:14)
    - Retirement Plan, 1964-1977 (Box-folder 30:15-16)
    - Speeches (Box-folder 30:17)
    - State Health Department Lists (Box-folder 30:18)
    - Virginia State Board of Dental Examiners, 1919, 1927-1931, 1938, 1953-1963 (Box-folder 30:19)
    - Virginia State Department of Health, Division of Dental Health Report, 1954 (Box-folder 30:20)
  - Federal Trade Commission Case, 1960-1978 (Box 30-31)
    - 1978 Document Request (Box-folder 30:21)
      A request for documents from the law firm representing the VDA in the FTC case. Folders 22-28 contain the requested documents.
    - 1978 Document Request: Brochures and Pamphlets on Dental Care, Adults and Children, 1960s and 1970s (Box-folder 30:22)
    - 1978 Document Request: Constitution and Bylaws, 1977 (Box-folder 30:23)
    - 1978 Document Request: National Children's Dental Health Week, 1973 (Box-folder 30:24)
    - 1978 Document Request: National Children's Dental Health Week, 1977 (Box-folder 30:25)
    - 1978 Document Request: National Children's Dental Health Week, 1978 (Box-folder 30:26)
    - 1978 Document Request: Newspaper Clippings 1977-1978 (Box-folder 30:27)
      The newspaper clippings discuss the public dental health initiatives and other non-profit activities in which the VDA had engaged.
    - 1978 Document Request: Peer Review Procedure Manual, 1976 (Box-folder 30:28)
      The manual was developed by the VDA and the Old Dominion Dental Society.
    - Documents Produced by Respondent, 1965-1977 (Box-folder 30:29-32)
      Documents relating to the governance and benefits of the VDA.
    - Virginia Respondents Exhibits, 1970-1977 (Box-folder 31:1-4)
      Documents relating to the VDA and the Northern Virginia Dental Society, both named in the FTC case.
- National, State, and Local Dental Organizations, 1923-1976 (Box 31)
  - American Association of Dental Editors, 1936-1939 (Box-folder 31:5)
  - American Dental Association: Board of Trustees Meeting Minutes, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 31:6)
  - American Dental Association: Bulletin of the Council on Legislation, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 31:7)
  - American Dental Association: Committee, Legislation, 1933-1934, 1938 (Box-folder 31:8)
  - American Dental Association: Committee, Publication, 1937 (Box-folder 31:9)
  - American Dental Association: Constitution, Bylaws, and Code of Ethics, 1933, 1957 (Box-folder 31:10)
  - American Dental Association: Correspondence, 1928-1935, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 31:11-13)
  - American Dental Association: Dental Education Plan, 1932 (Box-folder 31:14)
  - American Dental Association: Dental Student Recruitment Program for Local Dental Societies, 1958 (Box-folder 31:15)
  - American Dental Association: House of Delegates, Session Minutes, 1937-1939 (Box-folder 31:16)
  - American Dental Association: Insurance 1933-1935 (Box-folder 31:17)
  - American Dental Association: Membership 1929-1936, 1953-1961 (Box-folder 31:18-21)
    These files include dues information, junior and student member information, and membership statements.
  - American Dental Association: Miscellaneous (Box-folder 31:22)
  - American Dental Association: Newsletters, 1954 (Box-folder 31:23)
  - American Dental Association: Organization Chart, undated (Box-folder 31:24)
  - American Dental Association: Publications, 1936, 1953-1966 (Box-folder 31:25)
  - American Dental Association: Relief Commission, 1938-1939, 1951 (Box-folder 31:26)
  - American Dental Association: Research Commission, 1934 (Box-folder 31:27)
  - American Dental Association: Survey to Determine Dental Needs, 1934 (Box-folder 31:28)
  - Conference of State Society Officers, 1933, 1935-1937, 1939 (Box-folder 31:29)
  - Danville Dental Society, 1974 (Box-folder 31:30)
  - Delta Sigma Delta, 1971 (Box-folder 31:31)
  - Dental Institute of America, 1938 (Box-folder 31:32)
  - Detroit Dental Clinic Club, 1938 (Box-folder 31:33)
  - District of Columbia Dental Society, 1938 (Box-folder 31:34)
  - Lynchburg Dental Society, 1972 (Box-folder 31:35)
  - Metropolitan Area Dental Health Council, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 31:36)
  - Miscellaneous Publications (Box-folder 31:37)
  - National Board of Dental Examiners, 1929 (Box-folder 31:38)
  - Omicron Kappa Upsilon, Kappa Chapter (Box-folder 31:39)
  - Project Dentist Newsletter, 1935 (Box-folder 31:40)
  - Roanoke Valley Dental Society, 1923, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 31:41)
  - Southern California State Dental Association, Constitution, 1926 (Box-folder 31:42)
  - West Virginia State Dental Society, 1927, 1931, and 1933 (Box-folder 31:43)
- One Hundred Years of Dentistry in Virginia, 1869-1969, 1873-1969 (Box 32-34)
  - Address, Dentistry Fifty-Seven Years Ago, 1909 (Box-folder 32:1)
    Address delivered by Dr. Carter Perkins before the Virginia Dental Society.
  - Centennial Meeting, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 32:2)
  - Certificates (Box-folder 32:3)
    See also box 34 which contains oversized items from this file
  - Chewning, George H., 1873, 1878-1879, 1882-1889 (Box-folder 32:4)
    Former president (1887), items include letters, programs, and announcements.
  - Component Society Histories (Box-folder 32:5)
  - Dental Centenary Celebration Programs, 1940 (Box-folder 32:6)
  - Directory of Dentists, 1933, 1938, 1947, 1950 (Box-folder 32:7)
  - Early Virginia Dentists and Dentistry (Box-folder 32:8)
  - Essay, Dental History Past and Present, 1938 (Box-folder 32:9)
  - Historical Information (Box-folder 32:10)
  - Hodgkin, William Newton, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 32:11)
    Former president of the VDA, he had collected information on the history of dentistry in Virginia and this book was dedicated to him.
  - Hughes, John M., 1907, 1915-1919, 1927-1930, 1950-1968 (Box-folder 32:12)
    Former president of the VDA. Items include memos from the dental surgeon of the 29th Division of the American Expeditionary Forces, some correspondences, and some essays on dental practice and history.
  - Manuscript (Box-folder 32:13)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 32:14)
  - One Hundred Years of Dentistry in Virginia, Galley Sheets (Box-folder 32:15)
  - Past Presidents (Box-folder 32:16)
  - Photographs and Images (Box-folder 32:17)
    See also box 34 which contains oversized items from this file.
  - Powell, Hermie Wait (Box-folder 32:18)
  - Program, 1906 Annual Meeting (Box-folder 32:19)
  - Publications, Pamphlets, and Brochures (Box-folder 32:20)
  - Research Notes (Box-folder 33)
    This box contains typed note cards with information regarding the history of dentistry in Virginia, the VDA, dental legislation and procedures, and other related topics.
  - Saint Apollonia Images (Box-folder 32:21)
  - Southern Dental Journal, October 1882 (Box-folder 32:22)
  - Women's Auxiliary to the VDA, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 32:23)
  - Oversized Items (Box-folder 34)
    This box contains oversized items from the collection.
- VDA Journals, 1928-2011
  Please note that this is not a complete run of the journal.
  - Bulletin, 1928-1948, 1951-1956, and 1958-1964, Eight bound volumes. (Not boxed, on shelf)
  - Virginia Dental Journal, 1948, 1976-1983, 2004-2009, and 2011, 42 loose issues and 1 DVD-R containing volumes 81-85. (Box 37)